快点，孩子们  就好了
Hurry up, girls.  Nearly ready.
你戴的饰物太多了！
You have too much metal on you.
不算多
It's not so much.
我是个地方长官，不是亚洲之王
I'm a magistrate, not King of Asia.
给你妹妹一个
Give one to your sister.
给你妹妹一个！
Give one to your sister!
可不可以别烦我了 记得把头沙戴上
Will you stop fussing and put that veil on, please?
我们没时间了
We're going to be late.
大人，我向您致意
Patron, I kiss you.
很荣幸，玛比尼奥，找我何事？
Mabinio, you honor me. What do you want?
我…
I um...
那么，我就直说了
well, I'll go straight at it then.
我的尿壶在过去的9天内都被打破了
My piss pots were all broken this past nine day.
不知道是哪个军团的士兵们
Oh?  Soldiers, naming no legions,
认为把尿倒在老实的公民头上是件有趣的事情
thought it funny to tip them out over the heads of honest citizens.
现在，谁说就是士兵干的？
Now now, who's to say it were soldiers?
有可能是角斗士装扮士兵干的
Might have been gladiators simulating.
我看到他们的时候我能够认出士兵
I know soldiers when I see 'em
不是我有偏见
not as I'm prejudiced.
大部分士兵是好人，像你一样
Most soldiers are good men like yourself.
但是现在有许多外界因素…
But there's a lot of a foreign element these days
这样的事情不会再发生了  我希望不会再发生了
It won't happen again.  I should hope not.
罗马公民需要并且应该被尊敬
Roman citizens that need and deserve respect
但却被人用尿淋个净湿
are getting drenched in piss instead!
而且一滴尿都没给我剩下
There's not a drop left!
没有尿我怎么处理衣服？（尿液曾作为漂白剂）
How am I to make cloth without piss?
我怎么… 这样的事情不会再发生了！
How am I supposed to make   It won't happen again.
谢谢，大人
Thank you, Patron.
智慧神保佑您
Minerva keep you.
马思绪亚斯兄弟
Brother Mascius.
乌瑞纳斯兄弟
Ah, BrotherVorenus.
现在是个大人物了，嗯？
Big man now, eh?
你也不是什么小人物
You're not so small.
这些罗马婊子们
Ah... these Roman bitches.
自从我到这里后我就是干了后吃，吃了后再干
I've done nothing but fuck and eat and fuck since I got here.
兄弟，现在我们可不是普通大兵了
We're not under goatskin now, brother.
并无冒犯你女人之意
No disrespect to your women, huh?
我很想跟你再多谈谈 马思绪亚斯
I am pleased to speak with you more, Mascius,
但是我要先见我的客人
but I must see to my clients first.
否则的话他们会因为你插队而有意见的
And they are upset if not received in their proper order.
当然应该是这样
Of course, of course.
请原谅我这个当兵的粗鲁的行为
Excuse my crude soldier's ways.
什么风把你吹来了，马思绪亚斯？
What brings you here, Mascius?
只是来看看你怎么样了…
Oh, just seeing how you do...
看起来还不错啊
which is good, looks like.
我们的泰特斯·波罗在哪里？？
But where's that old Titus Pullo?
我不知道，有段时间没见他了
I don't know. I haven't seen him.
少来了！
Gerrae!
你跟波罗形影不离的啊
You and Pullo were like Castor and Pollux.
我已经不关心波罗的死活了
Pullo's dead to me.
很高兴你过得还不错
Well, I'm glad to see you're doing so good.
我们的老长官怎么样了？ 他还不错
How's our old chief then, eh?  He is well.
很好，很好
Good good.
说实话
I'll not lie,
弟兄们很不高兴，非常不高兴
your brothers are unhappy, very unhappy.
他们感觉老长官忘记他们的拥立之功
They feel the old chief's forgot who brung him here.
不能再发钱了，说好了的
They cannot have more coin. There is an agreement.
没错，没错
Ay, there is. There is.
钱是够多了
And it's adequate coin.
我在钱上还看到他的头像
Got his picture on it now I see.
铸钱的想用谁的头像是他们的事
A coiner may depict what he likes.
问题是，兄弟们需要的不仅仅是钱
Fact is, our brothers need more than just money
如果他们想要过上好日子
if they're to lead honorable and peaceful lives.
有一天钱用光了，那他们怎么办？
Money runs out one day, then what do they do?
怎么办？
What?
他们或许要去做生意？
They need to take up a trade maybe?
我看不太可能。他们还能做什么？
It's unlikely. What are they to do?
别跟我绕圈子，兄弟 有话直说
Do not pose questions at me, brother. Speak directly.
我们想要意大利的田地
We want land in ltaly.
只要恺撒能够做到，他就会给兄弟们土地的
Caesar will give all veterans land when he can
正如他承诺的一样，但是不是在意大利
as he promised he would, but not in ltaly.
恺撒给你的田地在意大利
Caesar gave you land in ltaly.
我是个地方长官，需要收入
I am a magistrate, and he must have an income.
而且我是一个人，而不是几个军团
But I am one man, not legions.
肯定很不错
Must be lovely.
我还没有看过我的地呢，太忙了
I haven't seen it yet. I'm too busy.
当然了…很忙，很忙
Of course. Busy busy.
我们不想无理取闹… 那就别这样
We don't want to be unreasonable   Then don't be.
我们有过约定的
We have an agreement.
我会跟弟兄们商量的
Talk it over with your man.
战神保佑你  也保佑你
Mars and Bellona keep you.  And you.
头，小心点
Cavi, Chief.
你好，波罗
Salve, Pullo.
怎么样？
How goes it?
来点睡鼠肉？
Want some mouse?
你应该尝点，这里的睡鼠肉很美味
You should. They do 'em savory here.
城里最好的睡鼠肉
Best mouse in the city.
那么…有什么工作给我吗？
So... do you have some work for me?
总有要买命的人
Always somebody needs mortality.
给我个名字
Give me a name.
问题是你需要谨慎
Trouble is, my honey, you want discretion.
你上次做的那单活
This last job?
你在艾文泰追那个人追得鸡飞狗走…
You ran that poor scurra up and down the Aventine
就像治安官抓小鸡
Iike Justice chasing chickens.
还不如到市场去这么做
Might as well have done it in the Forum.
我下次会干得无声无息的  我可不知道你会怎样
I'll go quiet next time.  I don't know.
我要为我的名声着想
I've my reputation to think of.
来找我买命的人
People come to me for their mortality work
知道我的手下都是很可靠的
because they know my men are reliable.  That's right.
没错，可靠的人
Reliable men.
下次我会安安静静的完成任务的
I'll be quiet as death next time.
明天这个时候过来
Come back tomorrow, same time.
乌宝会带你去认人的
Urbo will take you to your man.
先给我点酬金
Give me some money on spec.
不能在这里
Not here.
这里是招呼正经公民的端庄的地方
This is a respectable place for decent citizens.
他们想要我怎么做？
What would they have me do?
我又不能变出土地
I cannot make farmland.
是的，你可以这称之为驱逐
Certainly you can. It's called eviction.
我应该驱逐谁？ 你的敌人
And who shall I evict?  Your enemies.
敌人？我有敌人吗？
Enemies? I have enemies still?  Strange to say.
很奇怪你这么说
他们都已经变成朋友了
I shall make friends of them in time.
那么你手下的老兵就会成为敌人…
And make enemies of your veterans... unless something is done.
除非你做点什么
他们会不会转头反对我？
Is it possible they turn on me?
他们肯定不会起兵反对你…
They would never fight against you,
如果他们不满意
but if they're not satisfied
他们就会成为强盗…
they will turn to banditry and raiding.
打着你的名义…可不怎么好
In your name. Not good.
跟马思绪亚斯说
Tell Mascius
我尊重他的坦诚
I respect his honesty.
跟他说，那些老兵对我来说就像孩子一样
Tell him my veterans are as sons to me,
对于他们的忠诚，我打算给他们…
and to all loyal veterans I shall give good lands in...
波兰尼亚的土地肥沃美好的滩地
Pannonia. Good fertile bottomlands.
波兰尼亚？ 有什么想说的
Pannonia?  Speak freely.
那是个苦地方，而且很远
It's hard country, Pannonia, and far away.
马思绪亚斯不会接受的
Mascius will refuse it.
马思绪亚斯拥有老兵的信任吗？
Does Mascius have the men's full trust?
他能说服他们吗？
Can he sway them either way?
马思绪亚斯能说服第10军团的人，第10军团的人
He can sway the 10th men, and what the 10th men do will sway other legions.
会说服其它军团的人
那么给他个人点好处
Make him a personal offer then.
给多少？ 你自己拿主意吧
To what limit?  You be judge of that.
地方长官乌瑞纳斯…
Oh, Magistrate vorenus...
我侄女在下个集市日会开一个酒会
my niece is holding a symposium next market day
我希望你跟你的夫人能够成为我的客人
and I should like you and your wife to come as my guests.
我们的荣幸，长官
We are honored, sir.
你有问题？
You look troubled.
我跟我老婆都不太会跟人打交道
My wife and l are simple people, sir.
没关系，你应该适应上流社会
No matter. You shall get used to good society.
感觉如何？
How is it?
舒服多了
Much more comfortable.
我不认为我能够再背负西赛罗的称颂了
I don't think my back could take another of Cicero's eulogies.
他把你歌颂得无以伦比
No, he praises you so long and high,
人们可能都会认为他是发自内心的呢
one might think he was being sincere.
您好，大人  你好，公民
Salve, Magistrate.  Salve, citizen.
我丈夫回来了
My husband is home.
你们来看我真是太好了
It was so good of you to visit.
我相信你太客气了
Oh. Not at all, I'm sure.
下次再来，我很高兴接见你们
Please come again. I'd be so happy to receive you.
谢谢
Thank you.
别吹了
Desist that now.
她说…接见我们
Receive us, she says.
我… 女士们
I would   Ladies.
地方长官大人
Magistrate, sir.
丈夫… 这些是…？
Husband...  What are these now?
租来的，价格很合适
Leased, and at very good rates too.
他们看起来不好吗？
And don't they look impressive?
给他们多穿点衣服
Put some more cloth on 'em.
你看起来很累
You look tired.
为什么不躺会儿？
Why don't you lie down?
我到希望我能够躺会儿
I wish I could.
“依照元老以及人民的要求
"By claim of the Senate and people,
我们深爱的长辈盖乌斯·优利乌斯·恺撒
our beloved Father, Gaius Julius Caesar,
已经被尊为终身独裁者
has been declared Dictator for life.
此外，每年的第五个月在此后
Furthermore, the fifth month is
就将被称为”优利“以此来表示对他的敬意
henceforth name July in his honor."
擦掉它
Erase that.
卡西亚斯
Cassius.
这么做是没用的，每座山丘，每面墙上都有这样的图画
It will do no good. The image is on every wall, on every hill.
别担心这些涂鸦
Don't worry about those scribbles.
恺撒大帝知道你是他忠诚的朋友
King Caesar knows you're his loyal friend.
我对此倒不担心
Oh, I'm not worried about that.
只是我看起来真的是这样的吗？
No, it's just, do I truly look like that?
很像
It's near.
真是不幸
Well, how tragic.  Hmm.
但是图画可表现不出你的活力
But an image cannot catch your vim,
你高贵的活力
your noble vitality.
我说的都是真的
I speak only what's true.
大家认为你有像你先祖一样的行为风范
You have that grace in action they say your noble ancestor had.
这就是老百姓把你画到墙上的原因
That's why plebs put you on the walls.
他们在你身上看到了你先祖的影子  他们只是看到我可怜的姓氏而已
They see him in you.  They see my wretched name, that's all.
笨蛋，让我们说点别的
Simpletons. Let us speak of something else.
姓氏还是很有分量的，不是吗？
There's weight in names, isn't there?
你可以把猫叫成鱼，但是它还是不会游泳
You may call a cat a fish, but it will not swim.
老百姓渴望自由，以你的名义，他们…
The plebs love liberty. In your name they
他们可不会为了自由而做什么
They would not pluck a hair for liberty.
他们喜欢看上位人之间的斗争
Plebs like to see their betters fight.
看戏还要花钱，而且斗争中流的血都是真的
It's cheaper than theater and the blood is real.
来，跟我来
Come, come here with me.
你看
Look now. Look at that.
看看那个
是把椅子，怎么了？
It is a chair. What of it?
椅子？它是王座！
Chair? It's a throne!
我相信王座通常都装饰的很精美
I believe thrones are generally more decorative.
这不过是把普普通通的椅子
That is decidedly plain and chairlike.
你瞎了吗？
Are you blind?  Do not become hysterical.
别变得歇斯底里
Your mother said you were a coward. I begin to believe her.
你母亲说你是个胆小鬼，我开始相信她了
我的母亲很不高兴
My mother is very unhappy.
原谅我，我刚才说的有点过火
Forgive me. I spoke in anger.
我既不胆小也不瞎
I am no coward, nor am I blind.
我知道恺撒是什么
I know what Caesar is.
我能看出来
I can see.
但是我立过誓做他的朋友…
But I have pledged myself his friend
不，我是他的朋友
no, I am his friend.
那么，为了友谊
So for friendship
你就要让共和国灭亡？
you would let the Republic die?
我只是个人
I am just a man.
共和存亡的命运
The life or death of the Republic
不掌握在我手中！
is not in my hands!
你恰恰错了
You are precisely wrong.
共和的命运在你手中
The Republic is in your hands.
只有布鲁图斯去结束一个暴君的生命
The people will not accept a tyrant's death
才会被人民接受
unless a Brutus holds the knife.
你说的太过分了
Now you have gone too far.
他一定要死
He has to die.
你了解他，你知道他不会接受被流放的
You know him. You know he'd never accept exile.
他一定要死
He has to die.
等等，朋友
Wait, friend.
等等！
Wait!
Shh.
那个高卢屄感觉起来如何？
How's that Gaulish cunny then?
我猜肯定很湿滑吧
Greasy I bet.
除非我跟你说话，否则别废话
Don't talk unless I tell you.
来了，中间那个奥非的亚斯
There, in the middle. Aufidius.
凶手！凶手！
Murderer! Murderer!
凶手！
Murderer!
凶手！凶手！
Murderer! Murderer!
他杀了奥非的亚斯！
He killed Aufidiu!
奥非的亚斯！他杀了奥非的亚斯！
Murderer! He killed Aufidiu!
奥非的亚斯
Aufidiu. He killed Aufidiu! Murderer!
他杀了奥非的亚斯！
凶手！
Murderer! He killed Aufidiu!
凶手！他杀了奥非的亚斯！
凶手！凶手！
波兰尼亚？
Pannonia?
波兰尼亚可在900里之外
Pannonia is 900 miles away.
应该是600里左右吧
More like 600.
几乎在赫马尼亚那里甚至都不是罗马的一个省
In Germania practically. It's not even provinced.
他们说那里的土地又黑又肥
Soil's black and deep they say.
高大的森林满是野味
Tall forests, full of game.
到处都是日耳曼跟达迅强盗谁都不认识谁
Full of Teuton raiders and Dacian bandits and who knows who?
我们的弟兄们不想再打仗了
Our brothers don't want any more fighting.
他们不会再打仗了
They won't have it.
如果我们的弟兄们能够接受波兰尼亚
If our brothers accept Pannonia,
恺撒会对你非常感激
Caesar will be extremely grateful to you.
如何感激法？ 5,000便士
How so?  5,000 denarii.
我不明白你的意思  我想你明白的
I don't understand you.  I think you do.
从流第一滴血开始，我就以真心来对待我们的兄弟
I have been true to my brothers since I first spilled blood.
你以为我现在会因为5,000便士而背叛他们？
You think I would betray them now for 5,000 denarii?
那么就7千  也许2万还差不多
Seven then.  It might be 20,000.
我不像某些人那么贪婪
I am not so greedy as some.
某些人指谁？
Not so greedy as who?
我只是说我的尊严不能卖得太便宜
I merely say that my honor is not for sale so cheap.
如果你也支持波兰尼亚，你就没有出卖我们得兄弟
In favoring Pannonia, you would not betray our brothers.
如果他们不要波兰尼亚的田地，他们就什么也得不到
If they will not have Pannonia, they will have nothing.
我们手中有刀剑，不会饿死的  如果是那样，你们一样会死的
Men with swords never starve.  But they still die,
而且是当头的先死
captains first.
一万五  一万
15.  10.
一万二
12.
那么我就要远行了，兄弟
I'll be away then, brother.
很高兴跟你见面
Good to see you.
我也是
And you.
那个男人走了吗？ 走了
Has that man gone?  He has.
没事吧？ 你真美
Is this all right?  You look beautiful.
我害怕地简直无法呼吸
I'm so scared I can hardly breathe.
没事的
It will be fine.
亲爱的侄女，我已经有太多的事情要关注了
My dear girl, I have enough to worry about.
我不会因为一些涂鸦而就感到不安
I will not be fearful of graffiti.
我要告诉你，那些涂鸦里面说的事情可不是无中生有
I'm telling you, the scribblers are not wrong.
布鲁图斯会背叛你的
Brutus will betray you.
你似乎非常肯定
You seem very sure.
他母亲会迫使他这么做的
His mother will compel him.
见不到你死她是不会善罢罢休的
She will not rest until you are dead.
我想赛维莉娅对我已经没有什么兴趣了吧
I well imagine poor Servilia is not very fond of me,
但是说到真的想我死
but really, wants me dead?
阿提娅，你是多心了
Atia, you're a dramatist.
好吧，我已经警告你了，我就不多说了
Well, I've warned you. I'll say no more.
我已经警告他了
I've warned him.
你的心思不在这里
You're far away.
希望你想的是某个令人愉快的地方
Somewhere pleasant, I hope.
不过是一个人而已  我也是这么听说的
It's all one.  So they tell me.
我需要你的帮助
I need your help.
你妈妈是个狠心无情的人
Your mother is a vicious and heartless creature,
但我发现我…
but I find I am
已经不能没有她
wretched without her.
我已经尽力去讨好她
I have done my best to sway her,
但是她还是像躲麻风病人一样的躲着我
but still she shuns me like a leper.
甚至不跟我交谈
Refuses even to speak to me.
你能不能替我跟她说说
Will you talk to her for me?
让她知道我已经变得多么令人同情
Let her know how pitiful I have become?
没这个必要
There's no need.
她对你的高姿态不过是作戏
Her disdain for you is an act.
她是完完全全的被你迷住了
She is entirely infatuated with you.
这绝对是非常愚蠢的谎言！
That is a wicked, foolish lie!
阿提娅，我能跟你说几句话吗…
Atia, you let me speak with you
女儿，门边的那个女人是谁？
Daughter, that creature over there by the door, who is she?
衣着庸俗的那个美人？
The beauty in the vulgar dress?
她是跟着卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯来的
She's with Lucius vorenus.
我想是他妻子吧
His wife I expect.
真漂亮
It's so beautiful.
连天花板都被画装饰了起来
They've even painted the ceiling.
她身上那种浓郁的底层品味真是恰到好处
She has a wonderful tang of the street about her.
让我来介绍你
Let me introduce you.
我们也许应该四处走走  不，我们应该在这里等着
Maybe we should walk around.  No, we should wait.
他们向我们走过来了  镇定 镇定
They're coming towards us.  Calm calm.
地方行政官大人
Magistrate, my niece would like
我的侄女想要见见你可爱的妻子
to meet your lovely wife.  Honored.
不胜荣幸
内奥比 阿提娅
Niobe, Atia.
像你这样严厉的人是如何赢得这种美女的芳心的？
How did a grim thing like you win such a flower?
我遇到她的时候她还年幼无知
I found her when she was still young and foolish.
在我跟她幸运的丈夫谈事情的时候
Perhaps you will entertain Niobe
也许你应该款待内奥比
while I speak with her fortunate husband?
乐意之极
Delighted.
现在跟我说说是谁做了这么惊世骇俗的衣服？
Now, tell me, who on Gaia's earth
我做的  不会吧
made this astonishing dress?  I did.
是我做的
You didn't.  I did.
那么…马思绪亚斯是怎么说的？
So... what does Mascius say?
一万二，他接受波兰尼亚
He will accept Pannonia for 12.
非常好
very good.
我没想到他把自己卖得如此便宜
I did not think he would sell himself so cheap.
我应该让你去代我谈判所有的收买跟贿赂
I must send you to negotiate all my corruptions.
长官，我并不希望如此
I would rather not, sir.
说笑而已
I spoke in jest.
我明白
I understand.
这边请
Please.
你腐蚀了一个人
You have corrupted one man
但你却挽救了几千人变成盗贼的命运
and saved thousands from banditry.
我经常希望我能够回到高卢
I often wish I were back in Gaul.
一些简单轻松的战争的事务
There is something pleasingly simple about warfare.
乌瑞纳斯… 地方长官乌瑞纳斯，如果你能够这么称呼的话
vorenus   Magistrate vorenus, if you please.
我的孩子，他的地位现在高于你
He outranks you now, my boy.
很抱歉，地方长官乌瑞纳斯
Excuse me, Magistrate vorenus.
我听仆人传说
I hear rumor among the servants
泰特斯·波罗因为谋杀被关在地牢
that Titus Pullo is in the dungeons
正在等待审判
awaiting trial for murder. Is it true?
有这么回事吗？
It is.
是这样的
他被雇佣，成了一个刀手
He has been hiring himself out as a knifeman.
光天化日之下杀了一个人
He killed a man in broad daylight.
我们必须要帮帮他
We must do something for him.
我们不能帮他
We must do nothing.
不能？
Nothing?  The man he killed
他杀的人叫奥非的亚斯·登特
was Aufidius Dento,
西莲制钉协会的首席代表
Deputy Chief of the Caelian Nailmaker's Association.
他是个很受欢迎的人，而且他畅所欲言的批评我的领导能力
Popular man, apparently, and a vocal critic of my leadership.
人们将会猜想是我下令弄死他的
People will suspect I ordered his death.
我不能帮助波罗来授人以口实
I must not confirm those suspicions by helping Pullo.
那么是你
And did you...
下令弄死他的吗？
order his death?
直到他死了我才知道他的存在
I did not know he existed until he didn't.
我根本不知道他为何被杀了
I have no notion why he was killed.
像那样的公众人物应该会有很多原因
Public man like that, might be many reasons.
我不能让人看起来像是我派出我的士兵们
I can't appear to be sending out my soldiers
去杀掉任何反对我的人
to murder anyone who opposes me.
我这样会失去民众的支持的…
I would lose support of the plebeians...
或许乌瑞纳斯跟我可以…
Perhaps vorenus and l might be able to
任何跟我有关联的人也不能帮他
...nor can anyone associated with me help him.
他有什么朋友吗？
Has he any friends?
能帮他找个律师替他辩护？
Who will help him find a lawyer to defend him?
他是有罪的
He is guilty.
人们要看到公正的裁决
People must see justice done.
士兵们必须了解他们不是凌驾于法律之上的
Soldiers have to learn they're not above law.
我很抱歉，乌瑞纳斯我知道他就像你的兄弟一样
I'm sorry, vorenus. I know he is brother to you,
但是我们没得选择
but there is no choice.
都是真的
It's all true.
我想我们可以走了，除非你…
I think we can go now unless you
我们可以吗？这里非常好，只是…
Can we? This is very nice, but...
我了解
I know.
卡斯特
Castor... in the morning,
明早把泰门那个犹太人带来见我
bring Timon the Jew here.
母亲，晚安
Good night, Mother.
晚安，宝贝
Good night, my love.
我看不出来有什么问题啊
I don't see what's wrong with it.
Oh, Moses, you need law?
头号律师在这，在这！
Number one justice right here! Right here!
找我吧，老板！顶级律师！顶级律师！
Take me, boss! Top lawyer! Top lawyer!
你水平不错吧，啊？ 不错？
You're good are you?  Good?
我甚至能够替美狄亚洗脱罪名
I could have Medea acquitted. What's your case?
你的是哪个案子？
一个叫泰特斯·波罗的男人…
Man, name of Titus Pullo...
继续找吧，犹太佬  你不想接这个案子？
On your way, Jew.  You don't want the case?
我宁愿去替冥神吹箫！
I'd rather suck Pluto's thorny cock.
有人吗？
Anyone?
有人想要工作吗？
Anyone want work?
有人吗？
Anyone?
如果你说出谁雇佣了你，
It would go much easier for you
事情对你来说会简单很多
if you said who it was that paid you.
它能显示出你的悔罪
It it shows penitence.
对不起，帮不了你
I can't help you. Sorry.
我答应过不说的
I gave my word.
或者你急需钱来救助你生病的母亲？
Perhaps you need the money to help your sick mother
或者是有需要的朋友？
or a friend in need?
像这样事情将会对你有帮助的
Something like that would help.
我需要钱来买酒
I needed money for wine.
你有没有什么朋友的会为你辩解的？
Have  have you any friends that would speak for you?
肯定应该有的！
There must be someone.
这个面包不错，还有吗？
Good bread, this. Have you got any more?
泰特斯·波罗高卢13军团
Titus Pullo, soldier, 13th Gallic Legion;
被控凶杀
Accused ofhomicide
公民奥非的亚斯·登特
re citizen Aufidius Dento,
西莲山，佛伦那部族
Caelian Hill, tribe of Falerna;
他的朋友代他出席审判
Brought to trial by his friends.
让我们开始
We begin.
谁代表死者奥非的亚斯·登特？
Who speaks for the corpse of Aufidius Dento?
我…麦而斯·尼曲迪而斯
I... Maius Nigidius.
谁代表泰特斯·波罗？
Who speaks for Titus Pullo?
我 我…
I l
普瑞瑟斯 麦乌厄斯
Priscus Maevius.
原告，继续
Accusator, proceed.
公民们
Citizens,
朋友们…
friends...
当我被告知奥非的亚斯死讯的时候
when I was told of the death of Aufidiu,
我极度悲伤
I was deeply saddened.
一个好人被捅死，被屠杀！
A good man, stabbed! Butchered!
在大街上，光天化日之下被砍死！
Hacked to death in daylight on a public street!
我极度地悲伤
I was deeply saddened.
单是我并不惊讶
But I was not surprised.
这种惨剧已经变得很平常了
These horrors have become commonplace.
这种悲惨的例子
Wretched specimens like this
如同老鼠一样多
are common as rats.
我不会占用你们的时间，通过长篇的演说来验证他是有罪的
I will not take your time with lengthy proof of his guilt.
看看他！
Look at him!
问都不用问，我们都知道他有罪
It's not open to question. We all know he's guilty.
当我在地窖里看到老鼠的时候
When I find a rat in my cellar,
我不会问什么问题，我会让奴隶一脚踩死它
I don't ask questions, I have a slave squash him underfoot...
兄弟，你好
Salve, brother.
也向你问好，兄弟
And to you, brother.
不是太好，对吧？
Not good, eh?
你在这里干吗？我以为波罗对你来说已经死了
What are you doing here? I thought Pullo was dead to you?
很快他就要真的死了
Dead to all soon.
你还是像硬石一样顽固
Hard as adamant, you.
但是，你可能是错的
Well, you might be wrong, though.
许多人即将面对刀锋跟祭坛
Many's the slip 'tween knife and altar.
什么？ 波罗可不是孤单一人
What?  Pullo is not alone.
我们可不会让任何一个兄弟被这帮卑贱的乌合之众伤害
We'll not let any brother be damned by this dirty mob.
这帮狗头不久就会更大声的呼叫了
These dogs will be yelping louder soon.
当他们把他带下来的时候
When they bring him down off there,
我们就杀进去把他救走
we'll go in swinging and have him away.
叫他们走！ 为什么？
Call them off!  Eh? Why?
难道你不知道这件事到底是关于什么的吗？
Do you not understand what is at stake here?
波罗兄弟的命  政治
Brother Pullo's life.  Politically.
是关于政治
What is at stake politically.
政治，我操翻那个政治！
Politically. I fuck politically in her fat ass.
如果波罗被恺撒的手下救了
If Pullo is rescued by Caesar's men,
人们会以为是他下令弄死登特的
people will assume that he ordered Dento's killing
恺撒就要为此负责
and Caesar will be held responsible.
那又如何？恺撒能做任何他想做的事情
And so? Caesar can do as he likes.
他正在努力重建法律跟秩序
He is trying to re establish law and order.
但如果他的士兵杀人而不用承担后果
That won't work if his soldiers are seen
那么他就白忙了
to be killing citizens without consequence.
我现在还是不能让兄弟们走
Still. I can't call the boys off now.
为什么？ 因为这让我没面子
Why not?  Because it makes me look bad.
不这么做的话，你可能会更没面子
You could look far worse.
你会告发我们？
You will tell them?
如果需要，我会的
I will if I have to.
看着我，兄弟
Look at us, brother.
怎么会这样呢？
How has it come to this?
都是为了共和
It is for the good of the Republic.
所要付出的代价…
It's a worthy cause then.
快让他们走吧
Just call them off.
更加令人感到羞辱的是
To add insult to injury, this soldier,
这个不知哪里来的士兵，禽兽，野蛮人
this brute, this barbarian from who knows where,
拒绝供认他的雇主！
refuses to name his paymaster!
恺撒！恺撒！
Caesar! Caesar!
我们无法说出姓名来，公民们，我们不知道
We name no names, Citizen. We cannot know.
我们可以猜
We might guess.
我们可以好好的猜猜
We might very well guess,
但是我们不知道
but we cannot know.
这让他的罪行更加严重
Which makes his crime even worse.
有能够惩罚像这样的禽兽的刑罚吗？
Is there punishment enough for monsters such as this?
I think not. I think not.
但可能这位有学问的朋友
But perhaps my learned friend
能够告诉我们
can tell us otherwise.
普瑞瑟斯·麦乌厄斯发言
Priscus Maevius speaks.
这 这个人…
This this man...
不是别的而是一个无助的奴仆
is nothing but a helpless servant.
一个工具
Atool, a puppet.
一个傀儡
我们应该感到同情
We should feel pity, not anger.
而不是愤怒
怜悯他的…
Pity for his
怜悯他的堕落
pity for his degradation.
等等，你是否主张他无罪？
Wait. Do you claim him innocent?
不是，我只是要说…
No, I'm simply saying that
那么，如果你不否认他是有罪的，那我们就结束了
Well if you do not deny his guilt, then we're done with it.
你是否否认他是有罪的？
Do you deny his guilt?  No, I do not sir.
不，我不否认，长官  很好
泰特斯·波罗
very well. Titus Pullo
被判有罪，将在竞技场被处死刑
condemned to death in the arena.
你知道我一直把你当成我的儿子看待
You know that I have always looked on you as my son.
噢，天哪，一次那样的谈话
Oh dear, one of those conversations.
好棋
Hmm, good move.
我想要你帮个忙，就像父亲对儿子
I have a favor to ask of you, father to son.
我需要一个人帮我接收那个白痴维拉瑞而斯管理的马其顿
I need someone to take over Macedonia from that idiot valerius.
我想指派你去
I would like to appoint you.
我管理马其顿？
I govern Macedonia?
如果你接受的话
If you will accept.
以三个复仇女神的名义 为什么你要我管理马其顿？
Why by three Furies would you want me to govern Macedonia?
你是适合这个任务的人
You are the right man for the job.
我还真想不出几个不适合那个任务的人
I can think of few men less right.
布鲁图斯，你总是低估自己
Brutus, you've always underestimated yourself.
如果你尝试的话你会成就很大的事业
You might achieve great things if you would but try.
在马其顿？
In Macedonia?
我不这么想
I think not.
我要你再考虑考虑
I would ask you to reconsider.
我需要一个我可以信任的人去
I need someone I can trust.
你想要我离开罗马？ 不是这么回事
You need me out of Rome?  Not at all.
我需要你的帮助
I need your help.
一个你可以信任的人？
Someone you can trust?
难道我这么做错了吗？
Am I wrong to do so?
你心中有疑问，不是吗？ 我没有这么说
You have doubts, do you?  I did not say that.
我请你，坦白说
Speak plain, I beg you.
我有让你疑心的原因？
Have I given you reason for doubt?
既然你问了，如你所知的你有让我疑心的原因
Since you ask, you have as you well know.
你说的是几年前
You speak of years ago.
以前的背叛不意味着什么？
Old betrayals do not signify?
我没有背叛什么
I betrayed nothing.
如果你告诉我你要进军罗马
Had you told me you were to march on Rome
并要求我的效忠
and asked me for my allegiance,
我肯定会那样做的
I would have given it.
我可能会认为你是疯狂的…
I would have judged you insane...
但是我会献上我的忠诚
but I would have given you my allegiance
因为我把你看成父亲
because I look on you as my father.
布鲁图斯… 但是你没有要求
Brutus   But you did not ask for my allegiance.
我的效忠
你是在刀兵之后才要求我的效忠
You demanded it at swordpoint.
我什么都没有背叛！
I betrayed nothing!
原谅我，我说的有点过了
Forgive me, I spoke too hot.
你从来没有背叛过我
You have never betrayed me.
那么为什么你不信任我？
So why do you not trust me now?  I trust you completely.
我完全相信你
So much so that you would send me
如此信任，以至于要我
离开罗马去管理马其顿？
from Rome to govern Macedonia?
那么…
Well, thank you.
谢谢
I am honored, but I will not go.
我很荣幸
单是我不会去的
我有合法权力可以坚持你去
It is in my legal power to insist that you do go.
如同我父亲
As my father,
如同我父亲，我把你看成…
as my father I looked on you
就是一年作用，不会很长时间
For a year or so, no more.
知道城里稳定下令
Until the city is stable.
原谅我，我感觉不好
Forgive me. I feel unwell.
或许我们可以下次再下完这盘棋
Perhaps we can finish this game another time
理智点！
Be reasonable!
每面墙上都画着你用匕首刺向我喉咙的画！
You're on every wall with a knife at my throat!
不理睬这个迹象将是很蠢的做法
I would be foolish to ignore it.
只有暴君
Only tyrants
才需要担心暴君杀手
need worry about tyrant killers.
你又不是暴君
And you are no tyrant.
你不是告诉过我无数次吗？
Haven't you told me so many times?
你可以走了
You may go.
门神，大地女神跟冥神…
Janus, Gaia and Dis...
我虔诚的祈求
I humbly beg
你们能够接受这个虫子作为我给你们的祭礼
you accept this creature as my offering,
如果它能够让你们满意的话…
and if it pleases you...
我祈求你们保佑艾瑞纳长命百岁
I ask you to give Eirene long life.
也请保佑我的朋友卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯跟他的家人
And same for my friend Lucius vorenus and his family,
如果我的请求不是太过分的话
if it's not too much.
请让艾瑞纳知道
And letEirene know
我为我所做的感到抱歉
that I am sorry for what I did.
来吧，士兵，上来！
Come on, soldier, up!
这个要小心点…
Cavi with this one...
是战士
soldier.
来吧，懦夫！打吧！
Come on, coward! Fight!
站起来开打吧
Stand up and fight.
我不想打
I don't want to.
这样可不合规矩
That's not how it works.
你应该要反抗的
You're supposed to resist.
我不会反抗的，如果我不想的话
Not if I don't want to.
我只是想死，好吗？
I just want to die, all right?
动手杀了我吧，一切都会结束了
So come ahead and kill me and be done with it.
少瞎掰了，动手吧！
Bollocks. Move!
你有什么问题？你的尊严去哪儿了？
What's wrong with you? Where's your dignity?
起身战斗吧！
Get up and fight!
士兵！醒醒！
Hey, soldier. Wake up!
为什么你不过来帮我吹箫呢？
Why don't you come here and suck my cock?
听着，只需要你拿起剑
Look, just hold your sword.
站起来，拿着剑，就够了
Just stand up and hold it, that's all.
你不需要跑或什么的
You don't have to run about or anything.
你什么都不是，只是个懦夫而已
You're naught but a bloody mollie.
你跟13军团什么都不是，只是懦夫而已
You and the whole 13th! Naught but bloody mollies.
别扯到13军团
Don't talk of the 13th.
我他妈的尿到你们13军团！
Oh, eh? I piss on the 13th!
都是一群猪卵
Pig spawn, all of em.
为什么你不跟你们13军团排队来为我吹箫？
Why don't you and the 13th all line up and suck my cock
13军团！
13!
Heya!
13军团！
13!
波罗！波罗！
Pullo! Pullo! Pullo...
到了秋天，他们就消失了  谁？
In autumn, they disappear.  Who?
鳗鲡，他们都会消失
Eels, they all disappear.
是那样吗？ 哪里？
That so?  Where?
什么哪里？ 那么，他们去哪里了呢？
Where what?  Well, where do they go?
那些鳗鲡？ 这就是我想问的
The eels?  That's what I'm saying.
谁都不知道
Nobody knows. It's a mystery.
是个秘密
我等你很久了
Was expecting you time ago.
如果我们再次雇佣你
If we employ you again, next time,
下次最好别用老兵
best not use veterans.
母亲？
Mother?
我不再拥有恺撒的友谊了
I owe Caesar no more friendship.
我必须尽我的责任
I must do my duty.
我必须要跟卡西亚斯谈谈
I'll speak to Cassius.
看看我们能做什么
See what can be done.
翻译:TLF字幕组